<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary45.jpg"/>
            <dateline>Wednesday 5.</dateline>
            <p>The day was pleasnt, the water rough, however. This afternoon we had a
               threatened storm that didn't amount to much but it was magnificent to behold.
               The sunset was very fine too. In the open space between a bank of clouds that
               rested on the shore and those that covered the sun there was the richest
               [tracery?] in scarlet and vermillion, and above in the dark mess of clouds one
               open spot golden hued. </p>
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary46.jpg"/>
            <fw>Wednesday Mar. 5 continued</fw>
            <p>My company tried their rifles, shooting the rounds, at a [?] about
               200 yards off. They shot very accurately. The rocking of the boat prevented
               perfect accuracy of aim. I amused myself walking on deck, and writing
               a letter to the Chronicle. We despatched our letters this morning. We have
               such an abundance of fresh shad that we have got disgusted with it.
               Dr. Noble came on board and went to the Scout. Our surgeon is still sick
               in bed. He prescribes, however, and the [?] are experienced enough
               to get along. I hope he has received a lesson that he will not forget.</p>
            <p>I saw today the illustrations of the Bombardment of Ft. Barton in [?]
               Leslie adn New York Illus. news. The first is truthful but the latter is
               nothing at all like it except the ships, and those anyone can make.</p>
            <p>Our sutler got on board this day and has his goods. There is nothing to do
               here and much less to say about it. Each mess of officers have a table by themselves
               and the [styles?] are as various as the men. It is a much more comfortable
               way than the hotch potch we had before. We are no longer in danger of suffering
               for want of water, as we have a [?] was finished today, making 1400 gallons in
               24 hours. We usually consumed 700 gallons a day. We have just heard very 
               distrastrous new -- that Banks was defeated at Leesburg and 14,000 men taken prisoner.
               The news was brought her from the Pilot-boy. It is very improbable. He
               may however have crossed the Potomac, and they massed on him. It leaves us
               in horrible suspense until morning.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary46.jpg"/>            
            <dateline>Thursday 6.</dateline>
            <p>This was a delicious day. We were trying our Enfields again this moroning at
               about nine hundred yards. The boys were delighted that they could fire so effectively
               at such a distance. We can hardly blame reporters that they give such different accounts
               of things, for no two seem hardly seem to see alike. We were today discussing whether Lt.
               Selden, who lay dead at the embrasure in the battery we took, had boots on. 3
               or so asserted that he had top boots -- others that he wore shoes. We even located him at 
               different places in the battery. We are inclined to think that the story of Banks'
               defeat is a canard. Sgt was on shore and says teh report had been flying
               around there several days -- that they had papers to the 27th which said nothing
               about it. It is said that the Spaulding is to be in soon, and that we
               are not to go until it comes. We think that the ships are very nearly all
               embarked, on board the different vessels. I hope the Spaulding  will bring
               us a mail. I would like to hear some thing about what has happened
               since the taking of Savannah and Nashville. This is Lt Beaver's Birthday
               entering his twenty second year.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary46.jpg"/>
            <dateline>Friday 7</dateline>
            <p>There came up a storm last night, raing and snowing, and blowing fearfully, which
               continued through greater part of today. The Sound was very rough, boats could not leave
               the ship. We passed the day as usual. I got hold of Lansings pictorial fact book,
               and amused myself reading and copying the sketches. This evening the sunset
               was beautifully clear. We hardly think that we will sail before Monday.
               Tomorrow or Sunday it is not probable that we will start. Our surgeon still
               continues in bed, and we would not get another on account of the roughness
               of the sea. We had an argument this evening whether the expression "tomorrow
               is Saturday," or "tomorrow will be Saturday" is right. I took the former &amp;
               Shorkley the latter. It is an affirmation of the "tomorrow" abstractly --
               we wish to express the future will would be proper -- But to simply
               predicate that of tomorrow it is Saturday, I think the present can be used.
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary46.jpg"/>
            <dateline>Saturday 8th.</dateline>
            <p>This is a splendid day. It's pure adn bracing. The Sound nearly calm. Dr. Hassack
               turns up to-day to be sick with the varioloid. We sent two more men ashore today, Moseby [?]
               and Kause [?] That makes nine men we have in the hospital. We have another man taken
               with the symptoms, pain in the back &amp; limbs, &amp; may turn out of the same disease.
               We are still lying off Roanoke Island. The ships all appear to be in positions and loaded.
               with their freight. It looked lively and cheerful, &amp; we were in momentary expectation of
               orders to start. This is the day it is said that the draft men in North Carolina
               were to muster. There were two boats with troops went up the Sound, and it was 
               said they were going to Columbia, or the Albemarle, where one of the musters were
               to take place. I only hate this confinement on ship-board. It is breeding sickness
               fast. The Cap &amp; 1st Lieut of Co. I. were left on shore sick. Lt. [?] of Co. [?]
               has been sent from the Scout. The Adjt had a slight attack of hemmorhage of the 
               lungs today, and I heard it whispered that he was going to resign. The muster at [?]
               [?] is said to cover a loyal movement, and our expedition is said to be on hand for the [?]
               <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary47.jpg"/>
               <fw>Saturday March 8th contd.</fw>
               of aiding it. We had a fellow in one of our companies who shot a hole through his hand at
               Camp Union. He has been well cared for and required nursing day and night. When
               he could not bear the prssure of something or other the nurse held the artery. But 
               he is one of those who expects and demands all attention and shows not the slightest
               gratitude, but requires everything with a growl. The artery has frequently broken off
               and had to be retied -- in every instance almost owing to his ungovernable [?]. The 
               last time it broke was during one night that he wished to sit up, and he could 
               not sit unless propped and could not be propped without taking all the 
               blankets and coats of the nurses -- who were tired and wished to sleep &amp; refused, 
               and he broke into a fit of anger -- cursed &amp; swore -- and in the paroxysm the
               artery broke. It may require the loss of his arm to save his life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary47.jpg"/>
            <dateline>Sunday 9th</dateline>
            <p>This was the finest day we have had yet, especially in contrast with the stormy preceding
               ones. The air deliciously pure, the sun bright &amp; warm, so that it was relaxing to be on 
               deck. We had company inspection and the doctor inspected us too. We had to send 
               Knode adn Adam [Hemy?] on shore, the former with the mumps and the latter with 
               symptoms, either of fever or small pox. They were both very reluctant. We spent 
               the day reading, loafing and smoking. Lt. Beaver went on shore to see the sick. All are 
               doing very well except Kelly, whose face is swollen so as not to be recognizable. 
               [NAME?] has turned out small pox too. The vessels that went up the Sound re-
               turned this evening. There is a vague report that they have 2000 prisoners but is very
               improbable. The different regiments appear to fear our Regiment worse than the 
               rebels. It is [?] that we have the small pox bad. We have everybody
               that has the least symptoms of sickness sent ashore, and I really believe that 
               [?] Lt Lynch is the only officer that had the varoioid. He is doing very 
               well. Buskin &amp; Cap. Perkin are sick, but not with that disease. 
               The Col. was telling us taht there has been a quiet fight going on to oust our 
               Regiment from the expedition. There was an effort of the kind at Annapolis.
               There Dr. Church ordered our Regiment into camp, but Gen. Reno evinced a 
               determination to the contrary, and stood by us. The wish to have the glory ex-
               clusively Eastern. But our officers kept their eyes open, and Gen Reno happily
               being a Pennsylvanian has stood by us. The impression appears to be that we 
               will sail tomorrow at nine o'clock, but as to which way there seems to be 
               a doubt. Morris says we are going to Newbern. But why all the vessels
               and troops were brought up from Hatteras to return. The same route seems 
               queer. However there is no telling where it will be. One thing we feel confident 
               about is that our generals what they are doing, and will certainly take 
               us safely through. I am anxious to get papers and letters to Reno. What 
               they are doing in the outside world. We are to take three schooners in 
               tow.</p>            
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary47.jpg"/>
            <dateline>Monday 10th</dateline>
            <p>I think the news about Norfolk is a humbug. The navy not being ready 
               probably delayed us. I won't believe any reports any more. Alcott was on board 
               and told us that we were to go to Washington and march from there to Newbern 
               a distance of 35 miles. This may be true. An order came to have stairs up 
               at six o'clock in the morning and to follow the Northerner. The gunboats 
               went away some-place this afternoon, and is blowing fiercely this 
               afternoon. The Dr. told me he thought that Kelly would die. His face is swollen 
               very much, and he is a perfect scab from the crown of his head to the sole of his foot. 
               Our boys there tell us that it was owing to his impudence -- he would pull off 
               his clothes when he came there and caught cold. He was very stout and nasty, 
               [?] was always so cross-grained and ill-natured -- not ill natured -- but troublesome 
               &amp; contrary -- that he was a nuisance to Surgeon and Captain. He has not drilled 
               more than two weeks since he has been in the service. I regret very much that it 
               is so, for I rather liked him, and he did very well for the last two or three weeks, 
               after I had roughed him down. We can't expect to take all home with us, however. 
               The moon is shining tonight, and we have moonlight nights to fight under. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary47.jpg"/>
            <dateline>Tuesday 11th</dateline>
            <p>It rained this morning, but cleared off, cool and bright. The fleet got under weigh about 
               nine o'clock, and under steam and sail, with the Scout, Smith, and another schooner in tow 
               about four o'clock, the Cossack anchored in Pamlico sound off Hatteras Inlet. The New York 
               got aground just as she was rounding the point from Croatan into Roanoke Sound, and 
               the Admiral off long shoal way. The Cossack was the first steam transport in to anchorage  
               the gunboats, the [?], Hussar and other gunboats that carried troopers were here before us.</p>
            
            <fw>Tuesday March 11th 1862 continued.</fw> <p>The day passed without incident. I
               spent most of the day reading Lossing’s pictorial field book, so far as it
               related to North Carolina. One cannot help thinking that if they [slaves?] the
               same spirit as they did in the days of the revolution it will be a difficult
               matter to conquer. But their cause is not just as it was then - North Carolina
               is not in heart as it was then. The men are as brave no doubt: but their enemy
               is not three thousand miles away. There is not [Chatham?] in the Federal
               Congress, or any portion of the people in the North that espouse their cause.
               Their social institution is false at bottom. Capt [Ricot?] remarked to us that
               there would not be such an universal resistance if it were not for the women.
               In the [Michdenburg?] District in the days of the revolution the young ladies
               formed an association agreeing not to receive the attentions of any young man
               who did not join the army in defense of their country's rights, [?] a man who
               would not fight for his country, would not be fit to be a protector of them.
               Perhaps the feeling arises from the stories of rapes &amp; robberies told of
               our army - perhaps because it is said we would arm their slave against them.
               They know well that their husbands and brothers make concubines of their slaves
               - that the slave if freed might wreak their vengeance on them. If I were a
               Southern women my fears, if I honestly believed this of the northern design,
               would drive me to a desperation. A tug boat came along side telling us she has
               a mail for us - The last we had was about the 21st &amp; 22nd of February. 17
               days ago. That was the last newspaper news we received. This will [bring?] a
               little later. We appear more anxious to receive this than any other - perhaps
               in prospect of a battle near - and it will be the last time many of us will
               hear from home.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
