<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>James Merrill Linn Diary: 1861-1862</title>
            <author>James Merrill Linn</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>
                  <persName>Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
                  <orgName>Bucknell University </orgName>                 
               </name>
               <resp>Professor, Lead Investigator</resp>
            </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Junior Alejandro</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matteo Antenucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
                  
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>NinaArsov</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Caroline Colucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Drew Fisher</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Olivia Garcia</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Harvey Harvison</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Reilly Hope</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matti Kruger</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Selena Liu</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Gayda Makki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Maya</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Calvin McGuire</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Natalie Monroe</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Luke Nowicki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ori Raz</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Grayson Renkert</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Amadou Samb</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Samuels</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Rose Schmidt</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Nyah von Haam</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Bucknell University</authority>
            <address>
               <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
               <region>Pennsylvania</region>
               <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                  Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <sponsor>Bucknell University Special Collections and University Archives</sponsor>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary55.jpg"/>
            <dateline>Sunday April 6th</dateline>
            <p>Yesterday and the day before we did little else than fix up our camp. We had a
               short Regimental drill in the afternoon. Our men have forgotten some but the
               ground was very rough. In the afternoon we were blessed with the arrival of a
               very large mail from home. I received three letters from John &amp; 2 from
               Annie &amp; one from Laura. The last one is dated March 31st, so that it came
               through in five days. Both last evening this evening, Lt. Col. Bell and I took
               a stroll through the quiet old town. The streets are lined with high arching
               trees, and the leaves are just budding. There are many fine houses, but the
               beauty of them is in the large grounds around them and the shrubbery. Roses are
               blooming, &amp; the lilac &amp; locust are out. The multiforce is crowded. It
               must be a charming place, and one could not help thinking of the pleasant
               social times they must have had in times past. There is wealth and leisure.
               Where Capt Ritchie has his quarters, was the office and rooms of a bachelor
               Lawyer, built in a cross shape, &amp; the Col tells me has every luxury of
               library office, bed room, dining[?] bath &amp;c. It was said that at his
               parties, he always refused to drink wine, &amp; kept up the impression that he
               was temperate. His servant, whom Capt Ritchie has with him, on the Capt's
               observing a number of bottles in a closet marked "[haregonic?]" that he would
               at times drink a bottle of it, 
               <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary56.jpg"/>
               <fw>April 6. continued.</fw> and lie for a day or two, perfectly besotted. He
               was in that con- dition when the attack was made on Newbern, &amp; had to be
               carried away. We had company inspection in the forenoon. Tom. Grier came and
               took dinner with us. The day was delightful, &amp; we went up to the platforms
               &amp; one of the curtains is partially completed. I suppose that the alarms
               &amp; fuss last week was caused by a Dr Thompson of the First Brigade, making a
               false alarm. Morris said he had bought about 70 bales of cotton of an old
               fellow out in the country, and after he had paid the money, some rebel cavalry
               came down and burnt it. An order was read on dress parade last night, sending
               the doctor to report at Washington with the recommendation to the Secretary of
               War to dismiss him from service - that soldiers lost enough rest &amp; sleep
               not to be annoyed by false alarms and that all alarmists would be dealt
               summarily with. We formed under arms and marched into the Presbyterian church,
               where Mr Mallory preached. We heard also a part of the grand concert given by
               the 24th Mass Band, Gilmore's in front of Gen. Burnsides headquarters. After we
               got back we found all our men from Roanoke Island had got back except Murphy
               &amp; Adam Henry, how have [?] fever. We look very red &amp; some few will be
               marked. Poor Jim Kelly died on the 27th of March - he was delirious for 8 days
               and swore like a trooper until he died. It was owing to his impudence stripping
               stark naked - he was so selfruled they could not get him to take any care of
               himself. His side on which he lay was completely rotten - in fact he was one
               mass of corruption. I am glad the rest have gotten over it so happily. We have
               yet two cases on the other side of the River. We heard, through Gen Burnsides
               spies, who have just returned from Suffolk, that Gen. [Hendleman?] had taken
               Yorktown with 180 pieces of cannon. Our friends in the North appear to have
               been uneasy about us, for fear that we would get caught in a trap. Gen.
               Burnside has been kept thoroughly informed of everything that has taken place.
               His spies are everywhere, &amp; he has a very finely organized system. Many are
               New York detectives. Six of them were on board the Cossack, &amp; it was a long
               time before we knew who they were. They appeared and disappeared - where we
               never saw. One I remember did not come on board for a long time, when the
               morning we left Hatteras to come here, he suddenly turned up. You would take
               him for a Jersey huckster rather than a detective. We were on board a week with
               them when we had the prisoners. We kept the prisoners below except at certain
               hours, when the detectives would stay in their rooms. 
               <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary57.jpg"/>
               <fw>April 6 continued.</fw> It is wonderful that a change the appointment of
               Corporal has made on Charles Merrill. He is dressed very neatly and his hair
               and beard nicely trimmed, and appears to feel for the first time in his life
               that he has some responsibility. He does his work carefully and intelligently,
               &amp; take a great interest in it.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
