<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>James Merrill Linn Diary: 1861-1862</title>
            <author>James Merrill Linn</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>
                  <persName>Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
                  <orgName>Bucknell University </orgName>                 
               </name>
               <resp>Professor, Lead Investigator</resp>
            </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Junior Alejandro</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matteo Antenucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
                  
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>NinaArsov</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Caroline Colucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Drew Fisher</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Olivia Garcia</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Harvey Harvison</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Reilly Hope</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matti Kruger</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Selena Liu</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Gayda Makki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Maya</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Calvin McGuire</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Natalie Monroe</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Luke Nowicki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ori Raz</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Grayson Renkert</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Amadou Samb</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Samuels</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Rose Schmidt</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Nyah von Haam</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Bucknell University</authority>
            <address>
               <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
               <region>Pennsylvania</region>
               <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                  Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <sponsor>Bucknell University Special Collections and University Archives</sponsor>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary49.jpg"/>
            <dateline>Sunday March 24th 1862.</dateline>
            <p><note>This is mis-dated. March 24th was a Monday in 1862. It appears that Linn miscalculated and that this should have been Sunday March 23rd.</note> This morning Tom Grier and Chas. Kline came down from New Berne in a boat. They
               were with two officers who went down to visit the battle ground. But as they
               didn't come back at 1/2 past twelve we took the boat and went to New Berne. It
               is about a mile and a half or 2 miles by water. We landed by the Alice Price,
               and went to a three strong ware-house, washed yellow, looked like Tom's house
               at home. The rebels had used it for an ordinance room "No smoking" was painted
               on the door "Yankee devils" inside They did not suppose that we would see it.
               The room back used as an office was carpeted with cane, and nicely furnished -
               had a grate. Upstairs above, they had fitted up a nice room - carpet,
               bedsteads, mohair rocking chair, tables and chairs - fire place, with wood fire
               quite a library - which they had gathered from various houses in town. Even
               this gas fixture they had taken from some other house. This table had a fine
               tea set &amp; everything a house keeper watned furnished from the same source.
               I spent the afternoon &amp; evening with them and it was too luxurious. I
               walked with Yerkes to the Cemetery. There is a wall and arched gateway around
               it, built of a singular sort of [shelly?] conglomeration - would be very
               handsome if finished. But it all bears the air of neglect. Founded many years
               ago 1801 I think, by Christ Church transferred to the City of New Berne 1834 -
               it had many old graves in it - We noticed that of the Gaston - Wm &amp;
               Margaret. They had a singular way of putting a figure 1 before their figures,
               so that one tombstone which told of us of a sea Capt. that died on his passage
               from London to New Berne, in a certain lattitude and longi- tude, was aged 134
               years. Another was 156. - We begn to think they had made voyages enough and it
               were time he would cease going to down to the sea, when we discovered that it
               must be either a _fashion_ they had or the oldest people lived here since the
               days of the flood. We were pointed to a vault, which bore the marks of being
               pried open, from which it was said Gen Burnside recovered $45.000. One iron
               doored vault was open &amp; the coffins lay there exposed in a way that seemed
               awful to me. 
               <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary50.jpg"/>
               <fw>Sunday March 24. Continued</fw> We returned to the Gaston House &amp; then
               went back to Tom's quarters. Tom &amp; I started out to walk. Gen Burnsides
               Headquarters were in an elegant marble house, with a large well kept yard in
               front. The comical white guard tent pitched on the dark green grass, the two
               wel dressed sentinels pacing up &amp; down, the roses blooming in the yard, all
               made a striking picture. Near by was the lonly stacks of the chimnies of a
               whole half square burned down. Near by the Neuse river are several houses, and
               evidently stores burned. It looked odd to see a sign of "variety store"
               flaunting before a scene of desolation - It was curious to notice the vagaries
               that the fire caused in kegs of nails and other irons. The chimney stacks stood
               up, &amp; one could not help picturing the bright cheerful parlors where those
               fire places and grates were, adn beneath in the cellar lay the remains of the
               fire screen. We went up to the Car house &amp; railroad depot. Cannon balls
               &amp; shell lay all around &amp; in the Passenger Depot were cartrige boxes
               [belts?], &amp; [accountants?] of all kinds, shell of a new kind with a new
               kind with a brass [cork?], canister - a tin-case like a tomato can, filled with
               54 canister balls. They had evidently just dropped everything and run. From the
               letters we have picked up, they never dreamed of having to leave, &amp; yet the
               Richmond papers say New Berne is of no account. It is to us if not to them,
               though they must have esteemed it of some importance, from the amount of labour
               they have bestowed upon its defence. I concluded to stay all night and passed
               the evening cheerily by the bright fire place </p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
