<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>James Merrill Linn Diary: 1861-1862</title>
            <author>James Merrill Linn</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>
                  <persName>Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
                  <orgName>Bucknell University </orgName>                 
               </name>
               <resp>Professor, Lead Investigator</resp>
            </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Junior Alejandro</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matteo Antenucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
                  
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>NinaArsov</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Caroline Colucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Drew Fisher</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Olivia Garcia</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Harvey Harvison</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Reilly Hope</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matti Kruger</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Selena Liu</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Gayda Makki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Maya</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Calvin McGuire</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Natalie Monroe</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Luke Nowicki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ori Raz</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Grayson Renkert</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Amadou Samb</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Samuels</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Rose Schmidt</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Nyah von Haam</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Bucknell University</authority>
            <address>
               <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
               <region>Pennsylvania</region>
               <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                  Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <sponsor>Bucknell University Special Collections and University Archives</sponsor>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary23.jpg"/>
            <dateline>Wednesday January 15.</dateline>
            <p>It was foggy this morning. We could just see the "City of New York" laying out in
               the [?] A boat came in to our ship with five men - they had swamped two boats
               before they succeeded in getting off. The Captain lowered one of his boats, and
               he, the Mate, the Col and &amp; Dr [Hossack?]started out. They arrived just in
               time to see a little boat belonging to [?] Schooner take off the remaining crew.
               Both boats came up to see us at the same time and Captain Bennet called to us to
               cheer the little white boat, that had rescued the crew, which we did with a hearty
               good will. The capt and mate went away again and shortly after, the Brig "Hope"
               swung against us, pushed in our wheel house, and kept digging at us until it had
               all the out side works on the [starberd?] side, at the stern crushed - opened out
               our cabin knocking to pieces Capt Bell's berth. Mine just escaped. While this was
               going on we saw Capt Bennet returning: I was standing at the side as the Captain
               came up. Hi sboat shot past the place for getting on. He scolded his crew
               remarking with a forcible ejaculation that he "wouldn't give a handful of cow-dung
               for the whole of them" We got up steam, and the Brig was towed away, leaving our
               stern pretty well smashed on one side. The City of New York" was loaded with 70
               cases muskets and rifeles, ammunition, [hay?], shot and shell, and a great deal of
               Officers baggage. She is lying on her side one side stoved in - the poor fellows
               were on there for two days, and were clinging to her side when taken off. They had
               no sleep for two days, and were 15 &amp; 1/2 feet, and why she should attempt to
               cross with such a sea is owing to the government pilot. In calm sea she might have
               made it as the channel is 17 feet. The sailors were pretty well whiskeyed when we
               came on board. The Captain's name was Nye and the sailors spoke highly of him. The
               Quarter master, Shorkley, Beaver, Jones and I got a boat, and with little
               [Cubby?], a dark rich colored boy, with long dark locks, such luscious red lips
               and black eyes, and another sailor boy, with a game eye, and big quid of tobacco
               in his cheeck went over to the shore. We picked up some shells, saw Gen Williams
               and staff, and went into Fort Hatteras, which is built of sods, having barrels
               filled with sand for a foundation. There was a steam engine making fresh water,
               and a ten inch gun outside. Three or four wrecked schooners, masts and remains of
               many other wrecks on the shore. We had a gay time getting our boat off the beach -
               as the surf rolled heavily. This morning as we were standing on deck, we saw a
               boat run to shore, and they buried some poor sailor on the lonely beach. There
               will be nothing to mark his grave - the waves will soon smooth down the little
               hillock of sand - He'll always have storms and winds and dashing waves over him.
               The ninth New York 48th Penna are on this beach. Company C. 1st [W.I.?] Artillery
               have [?] Hatteras. Fort Clark is just above. Camp Bull is the N.Y. regiment &amp;
               five miles above Camp [blank] of the 48th. We hear that the New Hampshire Regt is
               to be landed &amp; the 9th N.Y. to go with us. Just as I was getting into the boat
               I shook hands with Morris - the first I have seen him since we left Annapolis.</p>
            <p>Capt. Neal as adj. gen. came on board this evening, and told us that Col. Allen of
               the 9th New Jersey and the surgeon of that Regiment were drowned. Their ship lay
               outside, and they came in on the yawl - and in returning were overset. Their
               bodies were recovered, and taken on board of the Highlander, a brig passing by. I
               saw their little boat dancing in the breakers, and afterwards saw the Highlander
               towed in, but I did not dream of the tragedy. I did not even observe that their
               bodies were lying on deck, as some of the rest did, and that they were rubbing
               there, and that their coats [?] up were those of officers. Just as they were
               taking the bodies below deck, one of our sailors said "pretty hard boys, but it
               can't be helped, drag 'em down." On the sern of one of the vessels which came in,
               a woman was sitting. One of our fellows in his ecstacy cried out, "that sight's
               worth a quarter, who shall I pay itto" turning round and plunging his hands into
               his pocket. The engineer of the City of New York, as he left the boat tore off the
               brass [?] in the engine room, and tied the colors around his neck.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
