<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>James Merrill Linn Diary: 1861-1862</title>
            <author>James Merrill Linn</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>
                  <persName>Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
                  <orgName>Bucknell University </orgName>                 
               </name>
               <resp>Professor, Lead Investigator</resp>
            </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Junior Alejandro</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matteo Antenucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
                  
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>NinaArsov</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Caroline Colucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Drew Fisher</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Olivia Garcia</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Harvey Harvison</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Reilly Hope</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matti Kruger</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Selena Liu</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Gayda Makki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Maya</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Calvin McGuire</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Natalie Monroe</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Luke Nowicki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ori Raz</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Grayson Renkert</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Amadou Samb</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Samuels</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Rose Schmidt</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Nyah von Haam</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Bucknell University</authority>
            <address>
               <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
               <region>Pennsylvania</region>
               <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                  Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <sponsor>Bucknell University Special Collections and University Archives</sponsor>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary38.jpg"/>
            <head>Sunday 9th </head>
            <p>I woke up this morning feeling as if I had been made for an old man eighty years
               old . My boots were scarcely dry, but fortunately the Chaplain of the 21st had
               found a can of lard and by a dint of greasing, and halling I got them on. I found
               outside quite a little town. Cabins nicely built in streets for the men &amp; log
               houses for the officers in the order of a regular camp. I saw a great many of the
               rebel prisoners - among them the Richmond Light infantry blues, Capt Wise’s
               company, which had so handsomely, entertained the New York 7th. They were fine
               aristocrat looking fellows in grey uniform like the Lewisburg greys. I found I was
               but two of three hundred yards from Reno’s quarters through the wood. It was a
               handsomer set of barracks than the others - the houses built of boards - the
               chimneys outside of mud and sticks plastered with mud. I found Beaver in the Col’s
               quarters &amp; the Col told me I need not go back as he had ordered the other
               companies to come up. During the forenoon I went down to see the forts - there
               were three - one of eleven one of four, the other of ten - this last one was the
               one that was bombarded but it had not been materially injured at all. They had
               spiked the guns, cut the ropes, threw most of the ammunition into the swamp. They
               are beautiful works built of sod and sand - and heavily armed with thirty two
               pounders some rifled - they are very formidable, &amp; well manned could not well
               be taken. </p>
            
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary39.jpg"/>
            <fw>Sunday 9th </fw>
            <p>The batteries, numbering three, are very nicely constructed of sod and sand. The
               fort just below here on the beach was called, Huger, now Reno, eleven guns next
               Blanchard, now Park, four guns mounted and a place for a fifth, lying on the shore
               at the landing - the third on Pig point, Bartow, now Fort Foster. This latter was
               not injured any of account. There were two red guns - one or two disabled. The
               barracks inside were burned and a great many arms destroyed. Houses outside were
               perforated with shot &amp; shell and we saw many lying far back of it. A great
               deal of powder had been thrown into the swamp, and are in case number of arms have
               been fished out of the swamps. On our way back, we met a party who had taken two
               prisoners. One a bright eyed fellow said he was from Craven County &amp; that his
               company had worked the guns themselves. The fourth shot had disabled the gun, and
               one man killed &amp; three wounded was all the casualties. Hassenplug found an old
               classmate of his when at Union College, Piot by name, from Murfreesboro' capt of a
               company. He knew John Blair Linn. They had long conversations of old times. He
               told us a great deal, which we did not altogether. I suppose they placed the same
               reliance on a great many of our statements. He said the army at Norfolk was 15.000
               that was on the Island on Saturday during the battle, and was so hard pressed that
               he left his overcoat. We heard the explosion of the fortification on Nags head on
               Saturday evening, but took it for an evening gun from a nine inch shell gun.
               Beaver picked up a tract “for the times” published at Petersburg Va. He has also
               one he took out of the cap of one that was shot in the last skirmish just before
               the the surrender near this camp. Casting our burden on the Lord by Joseph
               Atkinson. “There is no class of men who excite a deeper interest in every loyal
               son of the south than our gallant soldiers &amp; who have exposed them selves in
               defense of our honor our liberties &amp; our lives" The Col sent for the rest of
               our battalion &amp; our company arrived in the evening. They passed a most
               miserably wretched night, and said they felt very anxious about me. The barracks
               put up here will probably accommodate four regiments. There is every thing
               indicating an eye to comfort convenience and a permanent stay. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
