<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>James Merrill Linn Diary: 1861-1862</title>
            <author>James Merrill Linn</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>
                  <persName>Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
                  <orgName>Bucknell University </orgName>                 
               </name>
               <resp>Professor, Lead Investigator</resp>
            </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Junior Alejandro</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matteo Antenucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
                  
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>NinaArsov</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Caroline Colucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Drew Fisher</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Olivia Garcia</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Harvey Harvison</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Reilly Hope</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matti Kruger</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Selena Liu</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Gayda Makki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Maya</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Calvin McGuire</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Natalie Monroe</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Luke Nowicki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ori Raz</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Grayson Renkert</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Amadou Samb</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Samuels</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Rose Schmidt</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Nyah von Haam</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Bucknell University</authority>
            <address>
               <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
               <region>Pennsylvania</region>
               <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                  Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <sponsor>Bucknell University Special Collections and University Archives</sponsor>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="#"/>
            <dateline>Saturday 18 </dateline>
            
            <p>
               <note>Linn misdated this - in 1862 Saturday was the 19th of April.</note> We lay after getting off until near three o'clock when the Picket came down
               after us, and they found the mouth of the Pasquotank and proceeded. The Light
               house had been burned down so that our pilot, not a good one at best, could not
               find it. About five o'clock we reached the landing place, a sort of bend or
               pocket just below Elizabeth City. The three regiments had reached here about 2
               o'clock and had gone on. Our gun boats were lying here in force. The light
               boats took us off and ran as near shore as they could, then the small boats
               took us as near as they could, and we waded the rest of it. Very few but got in
               over the knees. After pulling off our boots and wringing our stockings we
               formed. We had been divided into two brigades - first of 3 regts. 9th N.Y. 89.
               N.Y. &amp; 6 N.H. and second Brigade 51st Penna &amp; 21 Mass. About seven
               o'clock we got under way. Two 4 horse wagons, with our combustibles and two
               pieces of cannon under Col. Howard ahead. The 21 Mass in the rear. We marched
               on some two miles and reached Curituck Court House. It was built of brick -
               there was a low jail, &amp; several houses around. We then marched on, through
               a beautiful country, well cultivated, nice houses, and over a nice clay road,
               which it was a pleasure to go over. After going about five miles we came to a
               hand board which said 8 miles to the river bridge, we turned into another road
               and halted. Suddenly the Maj of 21st came along, and the cry was to arms - we
               formed - but it was discovered that the first brigade had lost their way and
               went about ten miles around. We then proceeded, our brigade in advance. From
               twelve o'clock until towards one, we were marching very steadily, our men were
               dropping with fatigue, Morris rode along. I stopped &amp; told him our men were
               dropping out by scores - I was most miserably exhausted. I could scarcely move
               my legs. I had eaten nothing for two days, &amp; had a raging fever last night.
               We had observed a dense heavy smoke ahead, across the road extending over a
               considerable area of ground. We supposed it was a bridge burning. Morris had
               scarcely passed, when a cannon opened, and a six pound ball struck in a
               ploughed field about two hundred yards to our left, &amp; rolled and bounded on
               past. Immediately a discharge of canister followed. We halted. Got over into
               the field to our right and formed in line of battle. The cannonade was kept up,
               the canister striking in front and the round balls in front, and some went over
               our heads. We could see them quite plainly. But we could not see where they
               came from on account of the smoke. In crossing into the field, there was some
               confusion, and I ran after stragglers to get them into ranks. I had no
               assistance, as Shorkley was adjutant &amp; Beaver was aid to Lt Col Bell. We
               moved on into the woods and turned to the left. Here I was so completely
               exhausted that I begged Col Bell to give me Lt Beaver as I could not proceed.
               He told Beaver to take command, and I should stay as his aid until I recovered.
               We moved on through the woods. More than half of our men lay down completely
               exhausted &amp; worn out. The rebels kept our range and the round ball &amp;
               canister were crashing all around us. </p>
            
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary62.jpg"/>
            
            <p> We had one man killed, Hoffman of Hassenplug’s company and some wounded. He
               had his whole stomach knocked out with a piece of shell. I struggled on foot by
               foot. What most made me feel badly was that I should become exhausted just at
               such a critical time. But many were like officers &amp; men. We at last came to
               a road: the regiment was sent in to the left. I sat down &amp; lay down - I
               thought would die. Arnold came along and put a flask of whiskey to my lips and
               a few swallows revived me. We staid there, sending in all the stragglers. Col Bell sent for
               the 21st Mass - &amp; they came up in good order - they had stopped and rested.
               I had a large party of stragglers &amp; started in with them the direction the
               rest had gone. I met Gen Reno. He told me to keep down toward the left. He
               appeared to be mad about something. I went to the road &amp; then in. Lt
               Shorkley came out &amp; head the Mass 21 &amp; lead them into position to the
               right of us. By the time I got into a big oak tree. I saw Michael Shires co. K.
               streaking back, asked where his company was - said some were in there - I found
               there was no company K in battle - a sergt &amp; corporal all that was known to
               exist &amp; they with Blair. By this time my stragglers had fizzled out
               wonderfully - I had but two or three of my own men. I came on to my own men
               just then a few shots were fired, &amp; some one cried out don’t fire, they are
               our men. So Capt Blair shouted to our color bearer to raise their colors high.
               We soon found out who they were - the infernalist shower of bullets came in on
               us that I ever witnessed. Two of my men fell, Lanig, shot in the jaw &amp;
               Buskirk in the arm. But we gave them pepper back. The colors were a good mark
               to fire at &amp; I ordered them lowered. The 9th N. York made a charge - come
               out in beautiful order - but the distance was great and they were exhausted -
               the rebels played into them with canister &amp; ball - So they came over the
               fence onto us. I thought the rebels were charging us, &amp; gave my men orders
               to fix bayonets. I soon saw the red hats however. It did not make our men
               quiver, - they stood steadily firing. Directly we moved to the right, down
               along the fence - when the order was given to charge - Down went the fence,
               over we went pell-mell our flag ahead. Brouse of Hassenplug’s company fell shot
               through the head. I had just reached a ditch, when I felt a sharp pain in my
               side, &amp; sickness deathly - fell and was unconscious for a little while -
               but recovered &amp; staggered on, supported by some of my men. I am yet unable
               to say whether it was a faint or something struck me. I can’t find any mark.
               The rebels left. But we were unable to pursue, being too much exhausted. We
               formed &amp; I had the roll call, &amp; found four men, wounded - some missing
               - Lanig, Buskirk, McCormick, &amp; Vandine. </p>
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary63.jpg"/>

            <fw>Saturday 18.</fw>
            <p> We stacked arms &amp; and then got a drink of water. Several houses standing
               here had been burned, and the fences making dense smoke clear across the
               rebel's position so that we never saw the smoke of their cannon or musketry,
               until we got up very close. Our regiment was then moved to the right towards
               where we had been in the fight &amp; stacked arms in the open field. It began
               to rain very fiercely, and I went around to see the rebel positions. There were
               deep ditches along the road used as drains all through this country, which they
               used as rifle pits, having in front a worn fence partly thrown down &amp; high
               enough to get them cover. The road along which we advanced was very thickly
               strewn with rails so that we could not make a charge over it. After making
               coffee, we were marched to the cover of the wood along the fence where we had
               fought them, stacked arms and prepared to bivouac for the night. I went down to
               see our wounded. I came first to the hospital of the Zouaves, where I saw three
               of their dead lying outside - I was afraid to uncover their faces for fear that
               I would see Lanig. I went to half-mile further to our hospital. The rebels had
               played fiercely on our hospital, after the red flag was up round ball &amp;
               shell. The ground was all ploughed up. They must've seen the fight, for glasses
               were found by a man in Co. E at the place where their cannon were stationed.
               Lanig was shot in the jaw - jaw bone broken &amp; tongue cut off &amp; the ball
               lodged somewhere inside could not be found. Buskirk had a flesh wound through
               the upper part of me arm. McCormick wounded in the leg, via buckshot
               apparently, but no hole could be found in pants or drawers. Buskirk asked me to
               write to his father. Lt Lanig to his wife. He could not talk &amp; could only make some signs. Here Sergt Shuck Co. E came down to carry up Hoffman.
               Hoffman's brother was along - poor fellow - he took it very hard. I returned to
               our bivouac ground about nightfall. Beaver had got a gate, and we had a fire -
               made some coffee, &amp; after discussing the day and especially the
               incompetency of Major Shawl &amp; the cowardice of Capt. Shawl, we turned over
               to sleep, expecting to be called early, &amp; that tomorrow we would have a
               sharp work. I have not slept any for in about a half hour, nine o'clock. Lt.
               Col. Bell called us all up - the officers &amp; told us we should get our men
               ready to march in an hour back to Elizabeth City, that are safety depended on
               our doing it that night - the Gen Reno had reliable information that large
               reinforcements have been sent for and would be there before morning - the Mass
               Pickets could hear them coming already - each company butted arms stocked and
               dismissed; that arrangements had been made to take all the wounded that could
               be carried with safety, &amp; the rest would have to be left to fall into the
               hands of the rebels, that the surgeons had cast lots, &amp; the lot fallen on
               Dr. Warren 21st Mass to stay - Unless the march was made in perfect silence, we
               would be attacked by their cavalry, which we had seen in the distance &amp;
               supposed to be 1500 - so we went, &amp; wakend all our men. Explained to them
               all we deemed necessary to prevent them from imagining more. We had them load
               such of their pieces as were not, &amp; the 
               
               <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary64.jpg"/>
                caps taken off. Then Beaver came in
               &amp; told me the 21st had formed &amp; we were to form immediately. So we got
               out into the field - It was very dark. The Regiment formed in perfect silence.
               I cautioned my men that there was no occasion to be alarmed &amp; if anything
               took place they should stay quietly in ranks until they got orders. That any
               man that allowed his piece to be discharged, Gen. Reno would shoot &amp; if I
               found that any one had lost his piece in the morning I would have him punished
               by the severest punishment. The first Brigade moved first, then our Regt, Mass
               21 in rear - then two pieces of artillery - then our axe men, who had orders to
               destroy the bridges after they had passed - &amp; if cavalry came on they were
               to open out on each side - Col. Howard giving them time - and the artillery
               would play on them. We moved out onto the road. The first mile was very slow
               taking an hour or more - then we went faster - and such a march I can give but
               the faintest description. The roads which were good in the morning, owing to
               the rain, had become exceedingly bad. It was so dark that you would scarcely
               see the dark forms of the men in front of you. We were all excessively fatigued
               by what we had gone through previously. I was particularly unfit for it. But we
               stuck to it - to the color all the way through - it rained a great part of the
               time. In the morning, deep chalk holes cut in the road had been filled with
               wood in corduroy style, &amp; these were scattered and ricked around, so that
               the passage over them was rather precarious. Men fell down, &amp; sank in the
               mud - stragglers dropped out exhausted - some threw away their rifles though
               not many. When we reach the courthouse the glands of my legs swelled &amp; it
               was agony to stand still. It was near four o'clock. Stragglers came up &amp;
               joined us. Then I learned to my sorrow, that three of our wounded were left
               behind. It was agony to me for a while, though I know it could not be helped.
               In fact all the wounded of our Regt had been left &amp; of the other regiments
               except the dirty scoundrels the Hawkins Zouares. The surgeon of that Regiment
               was the medical director of the expedition &amp; he had loaded up only his own
               men. The Mass 21 had discovered the trick, &amp; got five of theirs along by
               getting a cart &amp; horse. We were very much chagrined. We left there &amp;
               got to the River Bank about five o'clock. Here we were very agreeably surprised
               to see Irvin of Hassenplug's company, who had been wounded in the arm join us.
               When he found the army had decamped, he knew when Col. Hawkins horse which had
               been wounded was tied went for it, &amp; rode through - swimming creeks - all
               the bridges had been broken down. We were glad of it. He said poor Buskirk
               urged him not to go.,</p> 
            <p>We had to wade out to a plank arrangement
               taken on the Pilot Boy &amp; put on board the Guide. Fortunately had dry socks
               in my haversack. Dick got me warm water, &amp; some officers kindly gave me
               liniment which I rubbed it on my leg - But I could not walk - only hop around.
               We got some breakfast &amp; went to bed. Yesterday is like a bad dream - I
               can't remember much about it - I was so used up - slept most of the time -
               &amp; sat around the stove - &amp; we fought everything over, &amp; traveled it
               again and again so that I feel perplexed about it. I know it was Sunday the 19
               just one year since I left home to enter the army. </p>
            
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
