<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>James Merrill Linn Diary: 1861-1862</title>
            <author>James Merrill Linn</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>
                  <persName>Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
                  <orgName>Bucknell University </orgName>                 
               </name>
               <resp>Professor, Lead Investigator</resp>
            </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Junior Alejandro</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matteo Antenucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
                  
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>NinaArsov</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Caroline Colucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Drew Fisher</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Olivia Garcia</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Harvey Harvison</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Reilly Hope</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matti Kruger</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Selena Liu</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Gayda Makki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Maya</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Calvin McGuire</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Natalie Monroe</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Luke Nowicki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ori Raz</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Grayson Renkert</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Amadou Samb</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Samuels</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Rose Schmidt</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Nyah von Haam</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Bucknell University</authority>
            <address>
               <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
               <region>Pennsylvania</region>
               <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                  Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <sponsor>Bucknell University Special Collections and University Archives</sponsor>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary29jpg.jpg"/>
            <head>Monday January 27th</head>
            <p>This morning was pure and delightful - the sound waters were calm and placid - all
               forenoon there was bjut the slightest ripple - We were on deck most of the morning
               watching the gunboats practicing with their guns. Lt Col Bell came over from the
               Scout - He told us that yesterday a small Rebel gunboat, bearing U.S. colors came
               into the inlet and lay within a hundred yards of the Scout. One of our gun-boats
               happening to go that way - she put up and off. That was real cute [They?] - much
               to be admired. Another part of the mail of the other day came in but no letters
               for me. Our life is so monotonous that slight things interest - &amp; it is
               interesting to watch how at one time we gather in knots and how the conversation
               floats from one topic to another, &amp; how the one group to another - Last night
               - Sunday - in the fore part of the evening [Gib?] &amp; I talked of home and many
               things that happened in our early lives - Shorkley Charley [Kline?] &amp; some
               other one got talking of Muncy, got around to [?town] Shirleysburg - Then at that
               town Capt Snyder floated in somehow - they got talking of stage coaches - that
               reminded the Capt of a story of [?] who got into a coach, with a woman with a baby
               - and [?] to put his hands in improper places - got his fingers daubed by
               mistaking the baby's posterior, for something else, exclaiming Coachman, stop this
               coach I am disgust - Then he told the story of a hair lipped fellow - which we
               recognized as the story of Chas McGregor &amp; the cow - Blair floated in -
               Shorkly &amp; I floated to bed - Blair wanted to know why we couldn't have roasted
               potatoes for breakfast &amp; thought they might be roasted in the galleys of the
               men. Other officers opposed interfering in anyway with the cook house of the men,
               giving them a chance to growl - Interfere it won't interfere says Blair. "They
               don't use those roasting places Who cares if they do talk if we really don't
               interfere with them" but he [posts?] to ascertain. Capt [Shawl?] officer of the
               guard, said he wished he had known Blair was going out he would have slipped out
               and ordered the Guard to allow no one to enter. Re-enter Blair "The cooks say that
               they will roast potatoes if they are taken out at five o'clock in the morning
               John" to John Smith Col's servant &amp; head <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary30.jpg"/>
               <fw>Monday Jan 27 continued.</fw> manager. "John did you hear" Shorkley, commisary
               general for the officers mess, from his berth above. "There'll be no roasted
               potatoes for breakfast in the morning. John" Blair, high tenor, "I was not saying
               there would be Lt. Shorkley, only ascertaining whether potatoes would be roasted"
               Blair 'high mad', and picks a quarrel with the adjutant, which was very comical at
               the time, but has faded out of my memory. Morning. John sounds the gong - Shorkley
               rises first: finds that the dog "general" has [cacapufied?] in front of my
               [berth?] has been tramped around - &amp; his stockings are daubed - flings them
               incontinently out - Mr Blair's light blue pants discovered lying on the floor -
               Blair informed of danger, examines - finds the light blues daubed - By the time
               all are up in that region &amp; the General receives a liberal cursing and sundry
               threats. Meanwhile Capt. Shawl is dressings is annoyed by our remarks - General is
               caught by the neck and summarily ejected - conversation and [objurgation continues
               until breakfast. Shorkley passes some severe remark about dogs in general &amp;
               the general in particular - Capt. Shawl unable to justify, [espouses?] the roast
               potatoes [aside?] and sayd he'd rather have roast potatoes than that tough biscuit
               But Blair ain't on that side now - he's adverse on the dog question. Blair comes
               to the second table - &amp; the dog question absorbs his attention - the only
               sharp remark amid all the filth, was that the dog would have to die a soldier's
               death if caught again, &amp; if he would have only staid on his own side ([id
               est?] the side the Shawl berth was on) "but a dog always hunts a clean place."
               Blair appears in dark blue. The roast potatoes appeared at dinner - It is remarked
               that Blair, usually very talkative wherever he is, is silent. Now we get an
               explanation of how so many of our towels have disappeared. Every one complains of
               having lost towels, one two or three. We thought some one must be laying in a
               stock - but we are told that during the days of the sickness, the General was sick
               too - he wawsn't particular where he put his accounts [cast up?] - on the sofas,
               on the carpet, and elsewhere - most generally inconvenient for the rest of us -
               &amp; the servant that cleaned them up generally seized on one of our towells,
               wiped it up &amp; cast it into the sea - So it is with the general as with the
               rest of us - when once the general attention of the community is drawn to a
               criminal all faults, crimes and misfortunes are fished up. I tremble for the
               general if he commits any other bad deed. His faults are not his faults - but is
               rather his misfortune. There thats a dirty sheet - but one can't give a full
               description of our life without mentioning such incidents. Some two weeks ago I
               threw out my chewing tobacco - Thursday I quit smoking until I can get on </p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
