<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>James Merrill Linn Diary: 1861-1862</title>
            <author>James Merrill Linn</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>
                  <persName>Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
                  <orgName>Bucknell University </orgName>                 
               </name>
               <resp>Professor, Lead Investigator</resp>
            </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Junior Alejandro</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matteo Antenucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
                  
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>NinaArsov</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Caroline Colucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Drew Fisher</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Olivia Garcia</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Harvey Harvison</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Reilly Hope</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matti Kruger</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Selena Liu</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Gayda Makki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Maya</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Calvin McGuire</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Natalie Monroe</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Luke Nowicki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ori Raz</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Grayson Renkert</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Amadou Samb</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Samuels</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Rose Schmidt</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Nyah von Haam</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Bucknell University</authority>
            <address>
               <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
               <region>Pennsylvania</region>
               <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                  Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <sponsor>Bucknell University Special Collections and University Archives</sponsor>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary44.jpg"/>
            <dateline>Saturday March 1st 1862.</dateline>
            <p>The morning was cold and clear - ice and a bleak wind blowing at all angles. Lt
               Shorkley and I intended to be off early, on a trip to the battle ground, but
               everything went wrong. As the wind was so variable, and the wooden chimney
               after burning half up, was found not to work, we adopted the expedient of
               cutting two pipe holes one out each side &amp; changing around the stove as the
               wind changed. We had the pipe out the north side, but as it smoked, Dick
               changed it to the South side - it smoked worse - so it was changed again to the
               north - then again to the east - and again to the north where it was found to
               do best, but miserable at [best?]. This occupied an hour and were smoked and
               frozen nearly to death - once Shorkley broke the elbow - We have the Stove on a
               box of sand, and it is pretty hard to move around. Dick in his efforts overset
               a pan of slop water over the floor &amp; began to swear - Beaver scolded -
               "Well between the smoking stove and oversetting that its enough to make any man
               swear." At last the stove took a slight notion to burn and the shad was frying
               briskly - I sat reading behind the stove - then was an exception - two pieces
               of fish flew out on the stove and floor - spattered me with hot fat &amp; my
               book all over. There never in all our house keeping such extraordinary trouble
               nor were we all ever in such a bad humor. At last we got breakfast about nine
               o'clock. Shorkley got started - went down past Park pt fort, along the beach
               about two miles, when a [major?] met us: we followed some one's truck and bound
               he had been fooled just as we were - we followed his track clear around the
               swamp back to the beach &amp; then tramped back to Gen Burnside's head
               quarters, crossed the camp of the 8th Conn &amp; took down a crooked road,
               reached the main road, and after a walk of three or four miles the old battery
               - Ft Russel We observed the trees marked with bullets more than 3/4 of a mile
               back of it, and near it every tree was scarred and cut. The battery was built
               in half moon shape, with three [?] very wide outside so as to give as wide a
               sweep as possible to the cannon. [?], where the 24 pdr Dahlgren was, swept the
               road - right in the centre. It was all cleared in front - &amp; the road runs
               straight down about 1/4 of a mile and then bends to the right - &amp; the wood
               is cleared so as that the road straight in front as also that of the bend. But
               right in front of the battery just where we crossed showed the most marks of
               bullets: two trees about 15-20 feet up were pierced through with cannon balls.
               The pine tree where we lay down was full of bullet holes. We then went down the
               familiar road, past where the field hospitals were, filled with groaning
               mangled men when we passed there last to the landing. The owner had come back -
               named Hayman, and it was at his landing instead of Ashby's where we landed. He
               said he was there until near sunset - that they did not expect us to land there
               but at Ashby's: that when he took is family across there the road was full of
               troops - Between the road leading to Ashby's &amp; this place there is a deep
               creek, and probably the rebels were afraid of losing their artillery, or they
               would have attacked us there. This battery is but a half mile across &amp; it
               could have been shelled by our gun boats had we known it. We walked down to
               where we landed and saw our broad swaths across the reedy shore - then went
               over to Ashby's We saw the young man there - he said he had been drafted - had
               gone up the canal bridge - &amp; his lot fell on him &amp; they were to go home
               and stay until called. From this landing where they expected us to land, there
               is a road leading through a swamp [?] - when the rebels were posted with two of
               their pieces that night they thought the water too low to land at Haymans. The
               Ashbys raised a white flag - &amp; the rebel officers threated to take them up.
               We saw the graves of our dead, one com. off Lieut Goodwin, &amp; one first
               Serjt [Jeremiah?] W Morse - [?] - 23rd Mass 27 in all - 1 unknown 2 prob N.Y.
               51 1 57th Penna. We returned the same way: met Alcott - had supper flour
               cake.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
