<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>James Merrill Linn Diary: 1861-1862</title>
            <author>James Merrill Linn</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>
                  <persName>Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
                  <orgName>Bucknell University </orgName>                 
               </name>
               <resp>Professor, Lead Investigator</resp>
            </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Junior Alejandro</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matteo Antenucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
                  
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>NinaArsov</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Caroline Colucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Drew Fisher</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Olivia Garcia</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Harvey Harvison</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Reilly Hope</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matti Kruger</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Selena Liu</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Gayda Makki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Maya</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Calvin McGuire</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Natalie Monroe</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Luke Nowicki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ori Raz</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Grayson Renkert</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Amadou Samb</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Samuels</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Rose Schmidt</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Nyah von Haam</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Bucknell University</authority>
            <address>
               <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
               <region>Pennsylvania</region>
               <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                  Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <sponsor>Bucknell University Special Collections and University Archives</sponsor>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary35.jpg"/>
            <dateline> Saturday 8. </dateline>
            <p>It rained incessantly all night and there was no sleep. We sat by a miserable
               little fire all night. Some times I dozed and dreamed of being in the comfortable
               cabin of of the Cossack, to wake with a start to find myself miserably cold and
               wet. So all passed the night. I don't know, but I think I suffered more than ever
               I did. Towards morning, perhaps between five and six, we all went over to the
               porch of the house, Shorkley, Beaver &amp; I, and though it was crowded, I sat
               down &amp; took a few winks of sleep. A few shots were fired, &amp; every body
               ran. We got back to our company and found them quietly standing behind their
               stacks, ready to take arms. We took arms, dressed, &amp; stood sometime, the alarm
               passed, I formed the men according to their numbers, we could not do it last
               night, divided them into platoons &amp; sections, and we stood in the drizzling
               rain. The different regiments formed, some had lapped with us in the darkness of
               the night. There were perhaps two thousand men there. Our regiment came out with
               over 800 men, My company 73. The first Brigade started about seven o'clock. Reno,
               Burnside were about. Morris came across to us with a great big sword with a steel
               scabbard buckled on him. None of the officers had their horses. "You'll soon have
               orders to march are you ready". "Yes". We teased Morris about his big sword he
               could scarcely draw it &amp; return it, it was so long. I saw Lt. Col Monteil
               cross the field to the house, the first time I had seen him since I sat as judge
               advocate </p>
            
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary36.jpg"/>
            
            <fw>Saturday continued. </fw>
            <p>about up past seven we heard some shots and then a volley of musketry. Foster was
               driving in the pickets. Then bang went the artillery then musketry and so it kept
               up. We moved up - the head of our brigade had already entered the wood, and our
               reg. still standing in the clear, when the first wounded man was carried along -
               then another and another - it was the most trying thing we had to endure. But the
               officers were all cool and calm, and every command was given in a clear voice,
               &amp; it seemed to keep the courage up. We passed up a narrow road through the
               wood, just wide as a wagon track, like our mountain roads, thickets of low pines
               and bushes. It was just like the roads up around Rengler’s' old mill - Then it was
               thick with wounded men carried and limping past us. Double quick - came to a mud
               puddle we were dainty at the first &amp; got around it, which broke us up a
               little, but the next one we dashed through. An occasional shell and bullet
               whistled, but we could see nothing but the regiment winding through the wood ahead
               - we turned off through the wood at a double quick, and got into another road -
               the battle we could hear, raged fiercely - every step we met wounded and dying and
               exhausted and some to whom we strongly suspected of being prematurely exhausted.
               An officer came and told me to send word to my Col. to send a company of
               skirmishers out to the right. I thought of aids &amp; officers giving orders
               without authority, but still determined to obey orders, and sent up Sergt Etwine
               with the order - The Col afterwards told me that some company at the head,
               relieved him of that agreeing to deploy. We passed the hospital which was so near
               that several men who carried the wounded there were killed. Zing goes a shell over
               our heads, and a piece struck a man lying down to rest &amp; killed him. We came
               to a halt - our regiment had turned to the left by order, but could not get
               through. My company was just at the point where we had turned from the road. The
               Col sent word forward that he couldn't advance on the left. The Rhode Island regt
               came through the wood and passed by the head of my co. up the road. I stood with
               the Col on a log at the fork of the roads when a volley of musketry passed over
               our heads accompanied with a shell. We got down rather suddenly. Here the bullets
               sung unpleasantly near. Orders came for us to leave so much of our Regt. as had
               passed the fork of the road and turn of the rest to the right up the road - There,
               thinks I, I am to lead the column. Everything was so uncertain, did not know where
               the enemy were, musketry sounded all over - all around - it was wood and brush
               &amp; nobody to be seen - we soon saw things however with more than the eye of
               faith. Co D Second company ahead of me was turned off leaving two companies and
               Lt. Col Bell in the thicket on the left - Double quick up, up we go - balls, shell
               flying somewhere - I saw Gen Reno at the corner of the wood - John Morris, then
               our brass field pieces, then all our other regiments lying flat down then an
               opening two or three hundred yards broad, then the battery of the enemy, the
               belching fire and smoke, the pail report of rattle of balls all around and above
               us- wanging into the trees - here we came into a swamp up to our knees in mud
               &amp; deeper - a poor fellow lie all doubled up beside a felled pine tree, we
               tramp on over him - we were in front of the enemies battery, in full view,
               crossing to gain their right - the swamp was tangled so that the regiment halted
               and we lay down right in front of the battery. The swamp was just like pine swamp
               - I've been in both and this was worse. Up again to run the gauntlet. We lay there
               some ten or twenty minutes flat on the ground. We gained the right and went
               plunging through the swamp up to our waists. Beaver was standing on a stump
               collecting the different companies - I never saw more than a half dozen of my
               company. I was standing on a stump looking ahead, when I saw Shorkley about ten
               yards ahead plunging through calling co. H. It bewildered me to see him there, I
               wondered how the rear of my company could have got there. Billy Allison, Brewer,
               Sergt Campbell &amp; Charles Merrill were with me generally and others who
               appeared and disappeared I rushed ahead and found that Shorkley had but two or
               three with him. He had cut across and got ahead of our colors - we still dispute
               how it happened, he alledging that I followed the Rhode Island colors. That
               couldn't be as the The Rhode Islanders were still further to our right. However
               Beaver appeared on a stump and he was calling to co. H away to the right to come
               over to the capt - We were certainly ahead of our colors, for they came up
               afterwards, part of our company having followed it. Here we halted and got
               collected. The Rhode Islanders on our right parallel. Here we heard a cheer. The
               back companies of our Regt were still in front of the battery, we all took it up
               and cheered when they told us our colors were planted on the enemy battery. <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary37.jpg"/> Just before it however, we saw a man on a tree making signals. one
               from our regiment stepped out without orders. the man disappeared. Charles Merrill
               was with me though and he kept on talking in his usual quiet way. He said he had
               been in pine swamp, but this was worse. He had been hardly able to do any service
               since he has been here, but he was one of the most quiet cheerful soldiers I ever
               saw &amp; he walked along waded rather, with his musket on his shoulder canteen
               and haversack just as if he were in the court room walking round the bar. We
               pushed on - the Rhode Island and ours got mixed. We came out on the right and the
               front of the battery Here we had to wade a pond up to our middle - but there was
               the battery. The right wing of our regt drawn up were marching on. We had to halt
               to form and it was near an hour before it put out and formed. By this time all the
               troops had left, and our battalion was ordered to remain at first to draw the
               guns, &amp; then to stay in the battery. I chafed at this - However while forming
               I left the company to go to the battery. Here I met Mr Mallory &amp; he shook
               hands congratulating our safe delivery. I remember saluting him just as we left
               our bivouac ground in the morning as we marched fast to go to the wood, and his
               face said "he might not see us again in life." We lost but two or three. I went on
               to the road on the left of the battery - just at the corner lay a dead man - and
               on the right just by the gun of the embrasure a handsome dark skinned man, black
               whiskers and mustache &amp; hair I noticed his delicate hands and small feet - he
               lay on his back his eye staring wide open, handsome even in his miserable
               surroundings - half imbedded in mud - hands blackened with powder - no uniform -
               had a pea jacket, and fine underclothes - with "Seldon" written on his undershirt
               and waistband of his drawers I learned afterward he was Lt. Seldon, son of Dr
               Seldon of Norfolk - that Col. Shaw cautioned him against exposing himself - "Damn
               them they can't hit me" he scarcely said it when he fell pierced through below the
               eye. At the centre gun lay a mule still in harness probably to draw off the gun -
               looked, very much, like as if it had its throat cut - but Col Jordan of the Rebels
               said it was killed by a mine-ball. Farther over lay a muscular man, with large red
               whiskers - a ball had struck him in the back of the head and his brain had oozed
               out into his hat until it was full. There were five or six dead men lay in the
               fort. A wall tent was pitched on the left. Two wounded rebel officers were laying
               there. Lt. Col. Patter who entered the fort from the left said that when a few of
               our men approached one of the them he cut at them with his sword, and on his
               asking him why, he did so, he said he had heard that we were ordered to give no
               quarter. If officers believed that, what should their men believe. We afterwards
               learned that they thought so, I had been told to by their officers. The most
               disagreeable thing was to see that the dead had been all robbed - pockets turned
               inside out - buttons cut off for relics. I was attracted to look at Seldon again,
               &amp; found his name had been cut out in both places. I walked around through the
               swamp &amp; dead bodies were lying scattered around through it. We had dragged one
               of the cannon some distance, when Burnside ordered them back, and the balance of
               our regiment were ordered to stay in the fort. Owing to the constant wet weather
               and exposure with no coffee or cooking utensils, all we had to eat was in our
               haversacks, Reno had ordered up whiskey. The officer in charge passed us, and
               wished Shawl to send a party in charge of a commissioned officer to bring some
               back to our men, as he would not deal it out until he reached head quarters Lt.
               Foster &amp; I were sent with ten men &amp; we followed up the grog for a couple
               of miles when we met Beaver 
               <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary38.jpg"/>
               <fw>Saturday 8th </fw> who was on with the advance, and had been sent back to
               order up the rest. I told him that we had been ordered to remain. He started back
               with us. We came to a crossroad, which he said was the road they went, but the
               officer in charge was perverse &amp; went straight on - we followed him &amp;
               Beaver left us. Up to the right was a house where Capt C. Jennings Wise lay
               mortally wounded with five wounds. A gentleman had picked up his gum blanket at
               the battle field &amp; I saw his name on it. The road was strewed with knapsacks,
               and other things thrown away. I met Gen. Foster on horseback - “Well” says he
               “boys we have gained a great victory - they have just surrendered to me two or
               three thousand, and the island is ours.” We threw up our caps and yelled. We came
               to a field - An old man and young man Islanders half drunk were explaining to us
               how they had been loyal men all the time. Then we travelled on - every one we met
               told us it was a couple of miles - We were dreadfully tired . We let the grog gang
               go, anxious to get some quarters as it was growing dark. Lost our road several
               times - at last after dark arrived in what seemed a little town, but was the
               enemy’s barracks. I stumbled into Col Upton, Mass 25th and asked permission to
               sleep on the floor. I pulled off my boots. There was an inch of water in them
               &amp; we had travelled 7 or 8 miles since we left the battle ground, &amp; I was
               rather sore . It was a grateful thing to lie on the cabin floor. Col Russel of the
               10th Conn was killed in the battle from concussion it is supposed of a passing
               cannon ball as there was no mark on him. One near him said he just doubled himself
               together and fell dead. We passed him on our way to the battle field. One of his
               men carrying him, crying called to us to give it to them, they had killed his Col.
               Capt Henry was killed too. He talked awhile complaining of pain in his stomach,
               but there was nothing, but a blue streak across his stomach. Lt. Col Monteil was
               also killed, he unnecessarily exposed himself, firing with his rifle in front of
               the battle, Frank Leslie’s artist was in close, behind a stump.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
