<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>James Merrill Linn Diary: 1861-1862</title>
            <author>James Merrill Linn</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>
                  <persName>Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
                  <orgName>Bucknell University </orgName>                 
               </name>
               <resp>Professor, Lead Investigator</resp>
            </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Junior Alejandro</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matteo Antenucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
                  
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>NinaArsov</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Caroline Colucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Drew Fisher</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Olivia Garcia</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Harvey Harvison</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Reilly Hope</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matti Kruger</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Selena Liu</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Gayda Makki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Maya</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Calvin McGuire</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Natalie Monroe</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Luke Nowicki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ori Raz</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Grayson Renkert</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Amadou Samb</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Samuels</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Rose Schmidt</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Nyah von Haam</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Bucknell University</authority>
            <address>
               <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
               <region>Pennsylvania</region>
               <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                  Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <sponsor>Bucknell University Special Collections and University Archives</sponsor>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary34.jpg"/>
            <dateline>Friday Feb 7 </dateline>
            <p>This morning it was clearer but rather cold. The gun boats has moved up into the
               Channel between Roanoke Island and the Tyrell shore. We kept moving up slowly too
               - the fleet passed a bend at the point of the island, and we could see them across
               the point of the shore. This took all the morning and we were eager spectators of
               the scene, until about half past eleven the gun boats opened on the batteries.
               Then commenced an awful cannonade. We watched the shells bursting in every
               direction, some high in mid air some low close to the ships, and our shells
               striking in every direction about the battery. A black smoke enveloped the battery
               - and the flames burst out - their barracks were on fire - twice they put them out
               and a third time they caught. We recognized the different boats - we especially
               admired a little sloop with one gun, which sailed like a duck up and down
               delivering her fire with emphasis. The Cossack ran up within perhaps four miles
               &amp; we had a beautiful and uninterrupted view of the my crossed our bow full,
               and drawing behind her about 30 surf boats filled with men. They stood over to our
               right. Just before this the Patuxent passed up with Reno on board - we cheered
               him. I got up on the hog-frame and waved my hat to Tom Grier, whom I saw on the
               hurricane deck. When the boats had got off to the right they laid there - about
               five o'clock the signal for disembarking was given. The Scout had been lashed
               along side of the Cossack during the afternoon. Lt. Col Bell in attempting to
               cross from the Scout fell down between the boats. Fortunately the wheels were not
               going, and he climbed up the paddles and came out the door of the wheel house.
            </p>
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary35.jpg"/>
            <fw>Friday 7.</fw>
            <p>Our boats had already been lowered. The two surf boats were to be towed by the
               small ones. Then Capt Bennet &amp; his little boy got into the small boat. The
               color guard, I noticed Peter Kozier, color corporal from our company among them,
               got into the boats and as many of Co. B. Capt Bell, as could got on board and put
               off. Co. A. Capt Bolton put off from the Scout. Soon Croatan Sound was full of
               little black specks moving toward the shore. I think there must have near five
               thousand men moved at once. There were a few houses standing on the shore, and we
               observed a company of rebels there but they ran as ours landed. We watched the
               first color planted on the shore and its black surrounding of men, then a second.
               It was now nearly dusk. The firing of the gunboats and battery had nearly ceased.
               One of the little black gunboats came near us - we observed his stern somewhat
               decomposed. On inquiring he said one of his steel guns burst and killed one man
               and wounded several others. We saw the Hunchback draw off with her and knocked
               out. The Delware covered the landing of the troops and the other gun boats formed
               in a line toward shore between the battery and the place of landing. We went below
               - coffee hot and smoking, warm bread and ham on the table, we thought to have a
               stomach full before we went. But the Deleware ran along side, and we were ordered
               off immediately - had hardly time to pour the scalding fluid down. It was now
               night - the moon struggling with fitful effort through the dark banks of clouds.
               The 8 companies were put on board and we left the Cossack. When the steamer was
               about a hundred yards from shore, a boat at the stern disembarked part of Co H
               with myself and we made the shore. I formed them and sent Dave Brewer up ahead to
               pick out the way. It was very dark and the ground boggy, so that it shook under
               our feet. Brewer had gone but a few yards when he suddenly disappeared, &amp; I
               saw him bobbing up on the other side of a ditch "look out Captain heres a well" We
               passed it safely, and got abreast the bow of the boat where I waited and formed
               the whole company with a few missing who turned up afterwards however. Then we had
               to travel through a swamp - a road had been formed of saplings but they were
               scattered and we often went in over boot top. We got on to terra firma pretty
               soon, and met Beaver, who was acting as an aid to the Col. who piloted us up to
               our place in the Regiment. We stacked arms, placed sentinels over the stacks, I
               cautioned the men about an alarm, that they should rise and take their places
               behind the stacks, and await orders to take arms. Then they dispersed to hunt wood
               &amp; bedding, cornstalks, brush &amp;c. There was a house and some outbuildings
               and fences. These latter were soon demolished to make fire wood, &amp; an
               apparently well fence clearing of about 8 acres was soon as open as any common. I
               got several split sticks &amp; Shorkly &amp; I lay down on them. He had a gum
               parachute &amp; I a small gum blanket. Beaver had nothing but a blue overcoat,
               which we had all put on one of each before we started. We lay an hour or two. It
               began to rain. Beaver got off to the porch of a house and shivered under a canvass
               tent. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
