<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>James Merrill Linn Diary: 1861-1862</title>
            <author>James Merrill Linn</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>
                  <persName>Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
                  <orgName>Bucknell University </orgName>                 
               </name>
               <resp>Professor, Lead Investigator</resp>
            </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Junior Alejandro</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matteo Antenucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
                  
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>NinaArsov</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Caroline Colucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Drew Fisher</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Olivia Garcia</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Harvey Harvison</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Reilly Hope</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matti Kruger</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Selena Liu</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Gayda Makki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Maya</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Calvin McGuire</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Natalie Monroe</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Luke Nowicki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ori Raz</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Grayson Renkert</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Amadou Samb</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Samuels</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Rose Schmidt</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Nyah von Haam</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Bucknell University</authority>
            <address>
               <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
               <region>Pennsylvania</region>
               <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                  Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <sponsor>Bucknell University Special Collections and University Archives</sponsor>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary79.jpg"/>
            <dateline>Wednesday 24.</dateline>
            <p>I went to New Bern this morning with Lt. Kelly to get him a leave of absence.
               We went to Gen. Reno who told us that in the present state of affairs he had
               concluded to give no leaves of absence or furloughs that if affairs at Richmond
               turned out as they expected, in about two weeks they intended to give leaves of
               absence to one or perhaps two officers of each company. As I was going down
               town I met an officer of the 48th who said the his field and staff wished to
               make some affidavits before me: I said I would meet them at any time between
               that and four o’clock at the Gaston House. He fixed twelve. About that time he
               came in a buggy with an invitation to dine with the Col. I refused to go and he
               then said they would come up to our camp tomorrow. They've got to come to me
               after this. Just after this there leapt of a schooner Moses B Something, came
               to me to make an affidavit to his log. He had been sent by Capt. Biggs out to
               our camp. I told him that I was as only Com. for Pennsylvania - but as if was
               for the Government to pay on - &amp; I’m the only civil personage in North
               Carolina I suppose it will answer. When I refused fees he appeared to be
               astonished, but I told him that so long as I was in the pay of the United
               States, I did not 
               <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary80.jpg"/>
               <fw>June 24. 1862 cont. </fw> consider it right to make money off [torn] ... Em
               French's whore-house has blown off [torn] ... There were a lot of officers
               there – she [torn] blackguarding them out of the windows [torn] calling them
               damned Yankee sons of bitches &amp; came out onto the porch with a revolver –
               Fired three shots rapidly, shooting a handsome young officer who was standing
               quietly in the middle of the street, in the abdomen. The soldiers were
               gathering and about gutting the house and preparing to hang Em French on the
               tree, when Robert Marshall Col Kurtz arrived – arresting four whores – handsome
               girls – Marching them down the middle of the street to the jail, and toting the
               dozen officers off as witnesses. Fred Etweine said this: he is one of those
               fellows that is always about when anything was going on. John Kenedy &amp; Jim.
               Gibson are such characters. To be shot by a whore – the officers that were
               inside – one standing on the porch with her – it's very disgraceful. Col. Kurtz
               in his wrath let out some forcible expressions about the way the house had been
               upheld. I met Sgt. Grassmine. He is a sort of detective in town. He told me he
               caught too small boatloads of salt going across the Neuse into the rebels
               lines. It rained this evening. I talked to the old d---- who said he was 104
               years old. He looks very ancient. His hair is not grizzled much, but his toe
               nails &amp; finger nails are scaly. I asked him whether he remembered the duel
               between Spaight and Stanley - he said he did well – the first fire Stanley was
               shot in the sleeve of his coat, and it came out his shoulder. The second
               Stanley shot straight through the breast. Spaight then wanted them to raise him
               up to fire a third time, but the second refused. He said the time was fixed and
               people went down from his county – 16 miles from New Bern to see the battle. He
               could not tell me where it took place. He said 
               <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary81.jpg"/>
               on this place his son [?] [?]
               &amp; it was bought by Jim Niley who afterwards fell in a duel with some one I
               have forgotten who. He [torn] Jack Stanley fell dead in the court House of
               Raleigh as he was taking some oath. He always said he was going to swear to a
               lie. He was a short old bachelor Jack Stanley was - he never was nobody after
               that - he told him often that he was no man after that- he had often ferried
               Jack Stanley over the river to go to Trenton to court. He evidently meant that
               he was struck with paralysis - as he speaks of talking to him afterwards - as
               was the fact </p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
