<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>James Merrill Linn Diary: 1861-1862</title>
            <author>James Merrill Linn</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>
                  <persName>Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
                  <orgName>Bucknell University </orgName>                 
               </name>
               <resp>Professor, Lead Investigator</resp>
            </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Junior Alejandro</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matteo Antenucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
                  
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>NinaArsov</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Caroline Colucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Drew Fisher</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Olivia Garcia</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Harvey Harvison</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Reilly Hope</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matti Kruger</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Selena Liu</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Gayda Makki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Maya</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Calvin McGuire</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Natalie Monroe</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Luke Nowicki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ori Raz</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Grayson Renkert</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Amadou Samb</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Samuels</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Rose Schmidt</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Nyah von Haam</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Bucknell University</authority>
            <address>
               <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
               <region>Pennsylvania</region>
               <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                  Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <sponsor>Bucknell University Special Collections and University Archives</sponsor>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary59.jpg"/>
            <fw>On Board Guide</fw> 
            <dateline>Thursday April 17. 1862</dateline>
            <p>Yesterday we got orders about noon to go on board the "Guide" with
               six days provision. In two hours we were on our march. Leaving all the sick we
               have seven hundred solid men with us. We marched through New Bern, past Gen
               Burnside's &amp; Reno's headquarters - The streets of the town are sandy like a
               sea-shore - the day was very hot - &amp; though equipped for light marching it
               was very hard on us. We went to the wharf at the Railroad Depot, on the
               Neuse?, &amp; the Pilot-Boy took us One wing at a time, down to the Guide
               lying below Town. The Guide is a very fine boat 32 feet longer than the Cossack
               - &amp; her style finer. We are quartered very comfortable, though the
               men are very much crowded, and between decks it is very hot. Capt Shawl as
               usual drunk as a fool - I was reading at the table when he came up, took the
               light and made a drunken endeavour to light his pipe. My first im- pression was
               that the wind had blown it out. As I looked up he had his pipe upside down,
               swaying to &amp; fro until he scorched his nose. "Don't you like it you can
               lump it" he said. I now register this now, that [twere?] I have excused his
               impertince, because he was drunk, but here after, I will go upon the rule of
               law as to drunkeness, that is - every man is supposed to know the consequences
               of his own [?]. He commenced talking about getting killed - that we were to
               have a battle on this expedition. I shall never vary my belief in his innate
               cowardice. The only time he kept sober was when he led us away from
               Centreville. He was drunk when we landed at Roanoke, he was drunk at the
               battle. He was drunk at Slocum's creek &amp; presented a most contemptible
               aspect - having fallen in the mud. The hair matress was too warm for me to
               sleep on, in the close state room, having slept in the open air for a month.
               Toward morning it became cooler &amp; I slept. I have today been better than I
               have been for sometime. I have been bothered with pain in the back, head and
               back of the neck &amp; stomach - I was not alarmed though they were symptoms of
               small-pox. But to-day my both hands broke out with red-spots &amp; pimples.
               There we are thinks I - only regretting that I was not back to New Berne, and
               the length of time it would put me off duty. However after looking at it
               suspiciously all day, I found they turned out to be watering pimples - Bless my
               soul - was ever man known to rejoice that he had caught the Itch - [?] it was -
               &amp; no small-pox -</p>
            
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary60.jpg"/>
            
            
            <fw>Thursday 17. continued. </fw>
            <p>We left New Berne about six o’clock. We looked with interest, at Slocum’s creek
               - but I spent most of the day on the confessions of Love queen. We passed
               Ocracoke inlet about 11 o’clock, passed a steamer, Port Royal, and 7 schooners
               - Hatteras inlet somewhat after one, and got aground between 4 &amp; 5 miles or
               so this side of Roanoke Island, just the place where the Guide got aground when
               we first went up. The Massasoit came down about dusk &amp; took our men off to
               lighten the boat. The Cossack passed us taking the sick and wounded north.
               There is something singular about this expedition. The N.Y. 51, Mass. 21. 48
               Penna were ordered to go on it. Lt. Col. Bell &amp; some of our officers were
               sitting on the Gen-Court Martial, &amp; Capt. Mitchel 51 N.Y. &amp; other
               officers had just got excused, to go on the expedition, &amp; they were
               twitting Lt Col. Bell on his noting left behind, when the order came
               countermanding the orders of other Regiments and our one substituted. The
               officers of the other Regiments are as mad as forty. An inspection of marching
               return showed that our Regiment has as many effective men as the other three
               together. Gen. Reno &amp; Burnside are to join us. Co. E. Capt Hassenplug’s
               Company had to go without a commissioned officer. Foster is evidently
               consumpted &amp; it will go hard with him if he gets home. He may attribute it
               all to his own work - dissipation especially at Harrisburg. When our Regiment
               came on board, one of the the hands asked where we were from - said that we
               were the quietest men he ever saw - It took but a half of hour before every man
               was quiet in his bunk - every other Regiment he said, in a half hour would have
               the ship upside down in a half hour. The Capt asked the Col. to make proper
               arrangements for order. The Col said he shouldn’t trouble about that - “Thats
               what the Cols of other regiments said &amp; we always had a row.” The Capt
               [bail] expressed himself agreeably surprised. He is a young man, highly
               educated, literary - mode sailor and though very young has been master for nine
               years. We are happily off now, but ...
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
