<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>James Merrill Linn Diary: 1861-1862</title>
            <author>James Merrill Linn</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>
                  <persName>Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
                  <orgName>Bucknell University </orgName>                 
               </name>
               <resp>Professor, Lead Investigator</resp>
            </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Junior Alejandro</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matteo Antenucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
                  
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>NinaArsov</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Caroline Colucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Drew Fisher</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Olivia Garcia</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Harvey Harvison</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Reilly Hope</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matti Kruger</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Selena Liu</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Gayda Makki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Maya</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Calvin McGuire</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Natalie Monroe</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Luke Nowicki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ori Raz</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Grayson Renkert</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Amadou Samb</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Samuels</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Rose Schmidt</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Nyah von Haam</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Bucknell University</authority>
            <address>
               <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
               <region>Pennsylvania</region>
               <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                  Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <sponsor>Bucknell University Special Collections and University Archives</sponsor>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary17.jpg"/>
            <dateline>On board Steamship Cossack Tuesday January 7 1862</dateline>
            <p>I slept splendidly last night and we turned out about seven o'clock. We began to
               wonder where breakfast was to come from, when Lt Shorkley was appointed commissary
               for the officers, and under his energetic supervision we had breakfast dinner and
               supper. He and Beaver were out nearly all day laying in a stock of provisions. The
               ship Cossack was formerly the Eastern [?] and is now painted black - it was
               evidently painted white before. It is an ocean steamer I think used between
               Portland Maine &amp; Boston or New York. It is about 300 feet long and sixty wide.
               The lady's cabin, the officers quarters, is about 30 or more feet long - has
               thirty berths, - Brussels carpet - dainty curtains - [secess?] - a washing place -
               large mirrors &amp; otherwise like all those large steamboats. This was a bright
               fine day, and this evening the moon is shining over the waters - the ships and
               steamboats with their signal lights - the light house - the snow covered banks -
               make a lovely scene - Add to this the bands in every ship are playing - Ours is
               now playing Dixie - they played it first before the general was beaten - as we
               left our camping ground yesterday. I amused myself up on deck with my glass - then
               reading A message from the sea. The wind was pretty high this morning : it rocked
               our boat very slightly. I felt the dizziness without exactly knowing exactly what
               it was until I look out of the windows and saw the waves running pretty high. We
               have everything embarked and ready except our horses. Another Regiment came down
               from Washington, I think a Connecticut Regiment, so that all are now embarked. The
               British ship [Imolita?], 37 Armstrong guns, is lying off the light house. Her
               officers were in town - Capt Hancock - and they told their officers that they had
               been sent to bring away Lord Lyons, had not the difficulty been settled. The
               British ungenerous exaltation over what they call our back - out, will only serve
               to increase that American feeling for a fight, which will burst out in violence
               some of these days. We have now an immense army - soldiers training for fight, and
               they will need employment. I received two letters by this mornings mail, one from
               John and one from Laura. When I come to think of it, it seemed like yesterday that
               I received it. This day has been long and short. John Morris was in and told us,
               that Gen Reno, had been so heartily disgusted with the 21st Mass. for being
               generally drunk, that he threatened to remove his staff from the Northerner to our
               boat. Maj. Clark urged him to wait till this morning, when he said if it were no
               better he would do so. Morris looks as gay riding around in the little boats as he
               does on his bay. He is very popular and the men think if any thing can be done
               Morris will do it. I was just coming down stairs to hunt berths for some men, when
               I met the officers of the boat rushing up stairs. I went our to the side &amp; saw
               the them lower the captain's gig in hot haste. I went out to the other side and
               heard the most agonizing scream of drowning men "I'm drowning" "let go my legs"
               &amp;c I waited until the officers returned. They reported they had rescued four
               men, one clinging to the wheel and three on the surf boards. The side wheel
               steamer run over a boat of the [?], [?] it is said with 23 men nineteen of whom
               were saved. I was in harrowing suspense until I found out that it was not one of
               our boats. [?] returned with three of our men just after it happened. Part of the
               8th Connecticut are on board the [?]. It was bright moonlight - we could see the
               men struggling in the water, and their screams were awful. I heard on firm manly
               voice raise above the din of the confusion, "Keep cool its all right" and at once
               it all seemed to subside. The side wheel boat has been considered the nuisance of
               these waters running in to every one. It must have been gross carelessness to have
               run into the boat on such a night as this.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
