<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>James Merrill Linn Diary: 1861-1862</title>
            <author>James Merrill Linn</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>
                  <persName>Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
                  <orgName>Bucknell University </orgName>                 
               </name>
               <resp>Professor, Lead Investigator</resp>
            </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Junior Alejandro</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matteo Antenucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
                  
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>NinaArsov</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Caroline Colucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Drew Fisher</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Olivia Garcia</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Harvey Harvison</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Reilly Hope</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matti Kruger</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Selena Liu</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Gayda Makki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Maya</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Calvin McGuire</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Natalie Monroe</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Luke Nowicki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ori Raz</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Grayson Renkert</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Amadou Samb</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Samuels</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Rose Schmidt</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Nyah von Haam</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Bucknell University</authority>
            <address>
               <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
               <region>Pennsylvania</region>
               <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                  Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <sponsor>Bucknell University Special Collections and University Archives</sponsor>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary21.jpg"/>
            <dateline>Sunday Jan 12.</dateline>
            <p>We got awake this morning, with [rocking?] boat, dense fog - many with sick
               stomachs. Some acknowledged it - others got quietly into their bunks and staid
               there. Beaver went to his bunk and was sick all day. The Col was struck suddenly
               after breakfast. Down in the hold and up on deck it was still worse. We stopped on
               account of the density of the fog and laid by until afternoon. We saw the Picket
               with Gen. Burnside on board. I felt a little reely after breakfast but an hour or
               two on deck settled, and this evening I feel splendid. This afternoon it cleared
               off, and I enjoyed the ride very much. We could see the low coast line to our
               right about two miles, strewed with the wrecks of ships. Toward five o'clock we
               came opposite Cape Hatteras, the wind blowing hard, and the sea very rough. There
               were several attacks of sickness - Beaver being out most of the afternoon, retires
               in intense disgust. We are now lying an and off Cape Hatteras waiting for a pilot.
               I was on the Hurricane deck at sunset - it was delightfully exhilerating - rising
               and falling with the waves - the spray breaking over the bow - the sunset was very
               beautiful the orange and saffire - the ashes of roses - the long low sand beach of
               Cape Hatteras, with its white shaft of Light House.</p>
            <p>Blair was officer of the day today - and luxuriated in the full reign of a sound
               stomach. The adjutant was sick as well as the sentinels at guard-mounting - &amp;
               Blair goes up and cooly tells them that no one should get sick without a written
               permit signed by the Colonel. The white sea birds followed in our wake a long
               while this afternoon on their untiring wing. We saw the Cossack as also the
               Steamship City of New York off Cape Hatteras. One of the Reporters told me that it
               was that ship, but I rather suppose it is one of the blockading flee. Along what
               is called Bald Beach, the wrecks of vessels are very numerous. One Schooner
               apparently lately wrecked, and what we took to be a tent pitched back of it. The
               ship is rolling heavily this evening, and it is said we will have to stay outside
               all night. Mr. Mallory told me this morning that they had heard in the Fortress
               yesterday afternoon the destination of the fleet - that the news came through
               directly from Norfolk - that we were to go to Hatteras Inlet, and our object was
               to blow up some locks of some canal, to prevent the egress of a Rebel expedition
               fitting out at Norfolk. It is said that there is a canal between Norfolk and
               Albemarle sound - I can't find anything on the maps I have with me, but I think
               there is what is called the dismal swamp canal. The Col's orders were to enter
               Hatteras Inlet and wait. It seems strange that we can keep the intelligence only
               from our own sailors. I was told by the World reporter that the notice of a
               traitor being found in the family of a distinguished military officer, was that of
               Adjt. Gen. Thomas, and his daughter was the one implicated. This information must
               have come through some such source. Thomas is a Virginian by birth and residence
               and on the breaking out of the war sent his slaves to Kentucky. I was told also,
               by the same man, that on Friday night, one of the officers detailed on the signal
               corps, was arrested endeavouring to escape over to Sewalls point, in a small boat,
               having with him all the signals to be used in the expedition. I see by [?] map the
               dismal swamp canal marked.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
