<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>James Merrill Linn Diary: 1861-1862</title>
            <author>James Merrill Linn</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>
                  <persName>Diane K. Jakacki</persName>
                  <orgName>Bucknell University </orgName>                 
               </name>
               <resp>Professor, Lead Investigator</resp>
            </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Junior Alejandro</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matteo Antenucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
                  
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>NinaArsov</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Caroline Colucci</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Drew Fisher</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Olivia Garcia</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Harvey Harvison</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Reilly Hope</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Matti Kruger</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Selena Liu</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Gayda Makki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Maya</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Calvin McGuire</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Natalie Monroe</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Luke Nowicki</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ori Raz</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Grayson Renkert</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Amadou Samb</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Ben Samuels</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Rose Schmidt</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
               <respStmt>
                  <name>
                     <persName>Nyah von Haam</persName>
                     <orgName>Bucknell University</orgName>
                  </name>
                  <resp>Encoding editor</resp>
               </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Bucknell University</authority>
            <address>
               <settlement>Lewisburg</settlement>
               <region>Pennsylvania</region>
               <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">
                  Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <sponsor>Bucknell University Special Collections and University Archives</sponsor>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <pb facs="https://leaf.bucknell.edu/sites/default/files/2026-01/diary19.jpg"/>
            <head>Thursday January 9 1862. Steamship Cossack.</head>
            <p>I was wakened this morning about 6 o'clock by the cry of a "man overboard." That
               cry is fearful enough at any time, but to be waked out of sleep, in the dark of
               the morning and hear it, and the cries of the drowning man, and that gulping noise
               he makes as he [be?] swept rapidly by the stern of the ship. However I was not
               startled. I got up however and tried to look out the window of Shorkly's berth. He
               was turned round and said there was no use of getting up, we must get used to
               these things. I went out to the back window and saw a number of little boats
               flying about. One husky voice - salty - I remember the first time I heard such a
               voice - the night we came down from Perrysville to Annapolis last spring when we
               were hailed by the Cumberland, and ordered to haul under his stern - I have
               noticed it since in all sailors - this husky voice called out "Keep the lad up"
               "Keep the lad up." Then again another just as husky cried out "I've got him"
               "Heave him up" "Put your arm around me, lad." Then I knew he was safe. In the army
               when they speak to a man, they say "My man" [on sea?] "My lad." The three rockets
               went up about seven o'clock - then one gun fired - and the first brigade got under
               way. Then two guns and our brigade started about a quart past eight. We have two
               ships in two - 7 &amp; 8 - 8 is the Scout with the balance of our Regiment. Gen
               Burnside in a small boat, eight or ten oarsmen, went shooting about from ship to
               ship - cheered by all of us as he passed. He had a common cavalry hat &amp; [gum?]
               coat. The bands saluted as he passed, we waved our hats, the men cheered. On each
               ship as it started the band commenced playing Dixie. I have spent most of the
               morning out looking at the fleet. How proudly they plough their way. Our vessel
               seems the staunchest and fastest sailor. I recognized Lt. Col. Potter on one of
               the ships (3) waved my hat to him, he turned to his men, did something in dumb
               show - but we heard a cheer burst from them, and we cheered in return. We passed
               the English [Imolite?] off the Light House. England is rousing a terrible feeling
               in our hearts. There will be a great war some of these days. I can't keep it down
               in myself. The officers spoke of it with an ill-concealed glare, that it was an
               insult to have that lying there. The ill concealed exultation of the British and
               their mentioning with such satisfaction that there are so many French war vessels
               on our coast, is making up the [desired?] indiganation in the breast of those most
               opposed to war, and least blood thirsty in feeling. [A?] five beels [at?] 2
               o'clock afternoon passed Cove pt, Drum point and the mouth of the Pautuxet River.
               This evening at the request of Bently reporter for the Philadelphia Enquirer, I
               wrote out a list of our company with their residences, and took it up to his room.
               He introduced me to McDonald the reporter for the Commercial Advertiser. Captain
               Bennet, Captain of my Boat came in and told us to come out and see a beautiful
               sight. He took us to the stern of the ship, [and?] see the wake of the ship. The
               moon was not very bright, the waters like dark green glass - a wake as broad as
               the ship, as straight as an arrow, extending as far back as the ships we had in
               tow, boiling an foaming white - It was indeed beautiful. We went back to the
               Reporter's room. Bennet gave us a succinct history of his life - 22 years at sea -
               master of a ship at 18 years of age - Keeper of the Minot Ledge light house -
               saved by being accidentally away when it washed into the sea - where he lost all
               his charts, drawings - having been three times around the world - were peculiarly
               valuable to him: joined his fate with Mayor Wood of New York - Capt of the 5th
               ward police - went into the custom house - had his head cut off for his connection
               with Mayor Wood - and with difficulty, and owing to his personal acquaintance with
               Welles and Burnside and his position here. He was superintendent of the outfitting
               of this fleet at New York. He has a little boy ten years old perhaps, that cried
               to go along. Burnside happened to be by. The boy said he would carry cartridges
               and do many other things - Burnside told him to take him along and he woudl allow
               him [?] While we were standing on the Hurricane deck this evening the sky was
               mottled white and long streaks dark along the western sky. Bently came over the
               sailors Rhyme [A anackered sky and make waves high And mares tails, and covers the
               ships sails.?]</p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
